טוב Tov everybody, today's דף daf is קייז, kuf yud zayin, 117,
and we pick up with the גמרא Gemara on the משנה. Mishna.
The משנה Mishna was about בנות צלפחד, benot Tzelofchad, and we are
going to now have a fun opportunity to discuss how the נחלה
nachala worked in when they for the generation that went into the
Land of Israel. So again, what the משנה Mishna says is that
the daughters of צלפחד Tzelofchad got three portions. You had here חפר,
Chefer,
you had צלפחד Tzelofchad and his brothers,
okay, you had a couple of brothers and here you had צלפחד,
Tzelofchad, okay, and then he died and you had his daughters.
All right, so, and it says that his daughters got three portions.
How did they get three portions? So it assumes that חפר Chefer
got a, that the people who got the portions in the Land
of Israel were those who left Egypt. All right, even though they
didn't enter in, we imagine it as if they had gotten their
portion and then they died in the מדבר midbar and then they
passed it on to those who went into the Land of Israel.
So the relevance of saying, and this is going to be the
question whether it is ליוצאי מצרים leyotzei Mitzrayim or לבאי הארץ. leba'ei
ha-aretz.
Okay, now the difference is you say who cares, everybody is getting
it anyway, but there's a big difference, right, because just imagine the
case of you have two brothers, okay, and this one has one
kid, and this one has ten kids, okay, and okay, these guys
went out of מצרים, Mitzrayim, these are יוצאי מצרים, yotzei Mitzrayim, and
these are באי הארץ. ba'ei ha-aretz. So if you, if you gave
it to יוצאי מצרים, yotzei Mitzrayim, these guys each got an equal
portion, okay, these guys each got an equal portion, they died in
the מדבר midbar and then this guy got one and these guys
all got a tenth, right, all of these cousins here, these cousins
got one-tenth of what their other of what their cousin got. That's
if you conceptualize it as we're going to give it to those
conceptually who left ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and then imagine that they
passed it on to their kids. If however you give it to
those who came into the land, then each every one of these,
these ten and this one are all going to get an equal
portion. Okay, you're going to divide up the number of portions based
on the number of people in the tribe, right, so the size
of the portions might be different, but at least relatively everybody here
is getting the same portion. So that's why it matters. So our
משנה Mishna assumes that it went to יוצאי מצרים. yotzei Mitzrayim. I
mean, excuse me, יוצאי מצרים. yotzei Mitzrayim. So if it went to
יוצאי מצרים, yotzei Mitzrayim, it assumes that חפר Chefer and צלפחד, Tzelofchad,
all of these people and his brothers, all came out of Egypt,
okay, although why it assumes that I don't know, because it sounds
like the brothers are also going into
מצרים, Mitzrayim, anyway fine, going into I mean going into the land.
Maybe it just assumes that צלפחד Tzelofchad was, I don't know if
it assumes that his brothers did. So I don't know, we'll bracket
that, okay, because צלפחד Tzelofchad died in the מדבר midbar and his
brothers sound as like they're going into ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So
let's just assume that צלפחד Tzelofchad came out of מצרים Mitzrayim and
he died in the מדבר midbar and these guys were born in
the מדבר midbar and they're going into ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So
the daughters got two portions, why did they get three portions? Portion
number one they got was, they got, you know, they got their
father's portion, that's what they obviously petitioned for, and they got their
father's portion. The other portion that they got is חפר Chefer died,
so חפר Chefer passes it on in the מדבר, midbar, right, like
everybody who went out of מצרים, Mitzrayim, okay, and he passed it
on to his kids. Okay, so we divide this up, I'm imagining
that there are two brothers, okay,
these each get one, each get one of those and he gets
two because he's the בכור. bechor. How do we know he's בכור
bechor we're going to learn it from פסוקים. pesukim. Okay, so he
gets three portions, now these portions are smaller than this portion. Not
equal size, but anyway he gets one portion as a brother and
an extra portion as a בכור bechor from his father. We'll put
a little ח, chet, these are חפר Chefer's portions, they're smaller, okay,
and his daughters get because he also died, these daughters get both
of his two portions, the regular and the בכור bechor portion. So
part of the חידוש chiddush here of this משנה Mishna is, number
one, it went to יוצאי מצרים, yotzei Mitzrayim, חידוש chiddush number two
is, the way the רשב"ם Rashbam says it, is that the daughters
will get even though there are also brothers, that they're still replacing
their father and they get together with the father's brothers. חידוש chiddush
number three I would say is, it's not at all obvious that
if the בכור bechor is dead that his heirs get the בכור
bechor portion even though they're taking the place of their father. So
they get a בכור bechor portion even though their father is dead.
And חידוש chiddush number four is normally we say a בכור bechor
doesn't get a double portion unless the father had it before the
father died, right, that's considered it has to be מוחזק. muchzak. But
the father didn't yet, he wasn't in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, he
didn't yet have the portion, it's only theoretical, right, and nevertheless we
said
that. of his portion in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and therefore he
passed it on and therefore צלפחד Tzelafchad got a double portion. Okay,
so that's what the משנה mishna teaches and now we're going to
see the גמרא. Gemara. Yes. So פרשת פנחס, Parshat Pinchas, was that
given before or after
the 40 years of wandering in the מדבר? midbar?
I mean, פשט, pshat, it's towards the end. So then why would
you at all think it's יוצאי מצרים? yotzei Mitzrayim? Because the whole
thing of נחלה nachala is פרשת פנחס, Parshat Pinchas, right? Right, no
no no. Clearly the פרשה parsha was said, לאלה תחלק הארץ, le'eleh
techalek ha'aretz, it's giving, we're going to go into the גמרא. Gemara.
Clearly the people, the פרשה parsha was said to the people that
were on the cusp of entering into ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. The
question is, are we still saying that conceptually it's your father's and
you're inheriting it? We'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. But if it's
your father, it goes back all the way to אברהם? Avraham? No
no no, just one generation. We'll see it in the גמרא. Gemara.
Yes. What's this large triangle to the right? If he gets the
double portion, yeah, but what's the other third? Where's the triangle? No,
the rectangle. What's the original? This? Yeah. He also gets a portion
because he went out of מצרים. Mitzrayim. He gets his own portion.
They both got it. Yeah, the assumption is that his father and
צלפחד Tzelafchad both left מצרים. Mitzrayim. Okay. And that's why he died
במדבר bamidbar because he left מצרים. Mitzrayim. Okay, let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. Well they say he died for a different
reason. No, he didn't die because of his sins, כי בחטאו מת.
ki vechet'o met. Right, well that's that whole thing about, right, that's
the מקושש, mekoshesh, right. Okay, תנן גמרא כמאן דאמר ליוצאי מצרים נתחלקה
הארץ. tnan Gemara keman de'amar leyotzei Mitzrayim netchalka ha'aretz. So the גמרא
Gemara says what we've just said, that our משנה mishna assumes that
it was divided to those who left Egypt. Okay, and that's how
it has this whole thing of that he died and he passed
it on and so on. Okay, ותניא רבי יאשיה אומר ליוצאי מצרים
נתחלקה הארץ, vetanya Rabi Yoshia omer leyotzei Mitzrayim netchalka ha'aretz, שנאמר לשמות
מטות אבותם ינחלו. shene'emar lishmot matot avotam yinchalu. It says they shall
inherit it according to the names of their fathers' tribes. So why
their fathers' tribes if it was given to them directly? So for
him, he says that that means that it's as if you gave
it to their father and they're inheriting it from their fathers. Now
of course we would say the פשט pshat here, it doesn't say
לבית אבותם ינחלו, lebeit avotam yinchalu, it says למטות אבותם lematot avotam
and we would naturally say that what it means is that first
you divide the land according to tribes and then within each tribe
you divide it according to the people of the tribe. But here
he's reading it, no, it means they're inheriting it from their fathers
or according to their fathers, you conceptualize it as if their fathers
got it when they left מצרים Mitzrayim and they're passing it on
to their kids. אלא מה אני מקיים, ela mah ani mekayem, so
what do I do with the verse לאלה תחלק הארץ בנחלה, le'eleh
techalek ha'aretz benachala, right? That's, I mean, it's clearly it's talking to
the דור המדבר dor hamidbar and it says, I mean, and to
the דור dor that's about to enter into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
and it says to these you shall divide the land. So it
says לאלה כאלה, le'eleh ka'eleh, it means that it has to be
like these להוציא את הטפלים, lehotzi et hatefelim, to exclude the, the
interesting, טפלים tefelim are like the secondary but it's also the way
the רשב"ם Rashbam says, it means like the טף, taf, the underaged
kids. What does that mean? It means that let's say somebody was
under, right, who was counted right there in the מדבר? midbar? The
people that were counted were basically the age of like twenty and
up, right? So if you were under twenty and you went into
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or you were under twenty and depending on
which generation you're focusing on, whether it's מצרים Mitzrayim or ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, you did not get a portion. So let's say somebody
left Egypt and they were nineteen years old and you said, and
you said it went to יוצאי מצרים. yotzei Mitzrayim. So that person
would not get a portion. Not only would he not get a
portion, now he grows up in the מדבר, midbar, he has a
wife, he gets kids, or whatever, his kids go into ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, they don't get either because it doesn't go to באי
הארץ, ba'ei ha'aretz, it goes to יוצאי מצרים. yotzei Mitzrayim. So if
you can somehow, it could somehow wind up that there are going
to be families that have no portion in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
which is like a strange idea, right? So would it just go
back to these people? Everybody who left, right, everybody who left under
the age of twenty and, right, everybody over twenty? No, right, it's
only if, right, thank you, it's only if you left under twenty
and your father was dead. Right. If you left under twenty and
your father came out with you from מצרים, Mitzrayim, right, then your
father gets and if, and then you get and so on. It
was only if you left, right, if you had left under twenty
and your father be dead and then you wouldn't and then you
would have a, yeah. All these people who were over twenty, they
all go killed in the מדבר. midbar. Right. So it's, yeah, so
it's kind of a strange equation. It's like you have to be
over twenty to get your portion but you are not going to
get it because you're dead. Exactly. It's going to pass down. Right.
You should have gotten it because you were the generation that was
supposed to enter it. Right. Yeah, exactly. Okay. So it's a very
interesting, let me just check the רשב"ם Rashbam that I'm there, just
one minute. Right, or בזכות משה Moshe *bizchus Moshe* if they didn't
have any מוריש *morish* that left מצרים Mitzrayim *Mitzrayim* without boys, בלא
בנים *belo banim*, then they didn't get a portion in the land,
אז לא נטלו חלק chelek בארץ ba'aretz. *az lo natlu chelek ba'aretz*,
right? Okay. Yeah, so that's it. So you have to have been
twenty if you left מצרים Mitzrayim *Mitzrayim*, as we learned כאלה ka'eleh
*ka’eleh*, you have to be like this generation, but ultimately it's given
to the previous generation. You are like the replacement of the previous
generation that should have been the ones to go in, so it's
only going to go to the previous generation based on those that
were the age of twenty. And it is possible if somebody left
again under the age of twenty and no father alive leaving מצרים
Mitzrayim, *Mitzrayim* that you would actually have the whole family not getting
a portion in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, *Eretz Yisrael*. רבי יונתן אומר
*Rebbe Yonatan Omer*, לבאי הארץ L'Ba'ei Ha'aretz, נתחלקה הארץ *l'va’ei ha'aretz nitchalka
ha'aretz*. So no, he disagrees. It's more פשט pshat *pshat* of the
פסוקים psukim. *psukim*. It goes to the ones that are entering in,
שנאמר לאלה תחלק הארץ L'eileh techalek ha'aretz. בנחלה *shene'emar la'eleh techalek ha'aretz
binchala*. That's good פשט Peshat, *pshat* of the פסוקים psukim *psukim*. אלא
Ella, מה אני מקיים לשמות מטות matot, אבותם ינחלו *Ella mah ani
mikayeim lishmos matos avosam yinchalu*? According to the names of the fathers
or the tribes of the fathers. משונה נחלה nachala זו מכל נחלות
שבעולם *Meshuna nachala zo mikol nachalos sheba'olam*. This is a different type
of inheritance from all other inheritances, שבכל נחלות שבעולם *shebechol nachalos sheba'olam*,
all other inheritances, חיים יורשין את המתים *chaim yorshin es hameisim*, the
living inherit from the dead, וכאן מתים יורשין את החיים *vekan meisim
yorshin es hachaim*. Here the dead inherit from the living. What does
that mean? So let's read the משל Mashal, *mashal* and then we'll
sort of spell it out. אמר רבי אמשול לך משל Mashal. *Amar
Rebbe emshol lach mashal*, let me give you an example. למה הדבר
דומה *L’ma hadavar domeh*? What is this similar to? לשני אחים כהנים
שהיו בעיר אחת *Lishenei achin kohanim shehayu be'ir achas*. Let's say you
had two brothers, Fred and John Cohen, okay, and they were living
in one city. ולאחד יש בן אחד ולאחד יש שני בנים *Uli’echad
yesh ben echad uli’echad yesh shenei vanim*. Fred’s got one kid, John’s
got two kids. Okay, and it was time to go ahead and
collect their תרומה *terumah* from the threshing floor. So Fred and John
say, you know, if we go ourselves, the guy who owns the,
the בעל הבית *ba’al habayis* here gives one equal portion to every
כהן *kohen* who comes to the door. You know, so let's send
our kids, then we'll get three portions between the two of us
rather than just two portions, okay, because presumably he wouldn't give with
the fathers and the kids together, okay. והלכו לגורן *V’halchu lagoren* and
so they went to the threshing floor. זה שיש לו בן אחד
נוטל חלק chelek אחד *Zeh sheyesh lo ben echad notel chelek echad*.
זה שיש לו שני בנים נוטל שני חלקים *Zeh sheyesh lo shenei
vanim notel shenei chalakim*. Oh, great great trick. ומחזירים אצל אבותיהם *Umachzirin
eitzel avoseihem*, the kids came and they give it back to their
fathers. The fathers have this whole deal going on. So what do
the fathers do? The fathers split the three between them. Each of
them gets one and a half. וחוזרים וחולקים בשווה *Vechozrin vecholkin b’shaveh*.
They each get one and a half and then, you know, and
then the fathers would then if they were to die would pass
it on to the kids. So it's like one of those classic
jokes, you know, we got this whole scheme going on. I could
tell you a lot of good Jewish jokes like that, but I
won't right now. Anyway. The best one is just the punchline is,
חיים *Chaim*, look who's telling us how to do business. Okay anyway.
But okay, for anyway. So what does that mean? What that means
is the following is that, you know, we'll use this, is that
he says, what? A Ponzi scheme. Exactly. Anyway, it means the sons
are sent, the sons are sent to collect the תרומה *terumah*, the
sons are the ones that are באי הארץ Ba'ei Ha'aretz *ba’ei ha'aretz*
so they get the portion. So in this case there'd be like
eleven portions, okay, right? And then this guy gets his one. They
all go back to the fathers, okay. Now you have, let's assume
this is nine and one, right? Because there are nine kids. These
are the באי הארץ Ba'ei Ha'aretz *ba’ei ha'aretz*. We'll assume that there
are nine kids here, okay. This is you know, ראובן *Reuven* has
nine and whatever שמעון *Shimon* has one. Goes back if these are
brothers, they split it up. So this guy now gets five
and this guy gets five.
Okay, and then there are ten remember, so that's מתים יורשים את
החיים metim yorshim et hachaim? *meisim yorshim es hachaim*. You've like passed
it back to their fathers. Their fathers died, now it passes it
back down. Okay now this guy's got still not going to be
fair in the sense that they're not going to get equal sized
portions, but it's going to be a little fairer. Between these nine
they're going to get five and this one is going to get
five. Okay
so so at least it's a little fairer, right? But it's not
fair. What's not fair? What's not fair is at least from their
perspective this guy who's part of a smaller family, he gets much
more than each of us gets.
Okay actually, actually I take it back. It's the exact same unfairness.
Right, because this is all, he gets one portion and they get
the same size portion between the nine of them. So actually right,
so actually it's the same inequity between them. The reason it's different,
so then you say why bother? Right at the end of the
day at the end of the day he got one side, he
got one side, you know all these nine all this nine got
one. So why didn't you just give it to them and have
them be מוותר *mevater*? So it does not matter between the brothers.
Between the brothers it's not have mattered if you started here and
went down or you started here went up and went down. You
know what it mattered? For them in a different family,
right, because... If this is, if this, right, this is one family
and here is another family. So in this other family, right, let's
just say it's one guy and one kid. All right. So, wait
let me think.
So how would it work? So if it was,
yeah, what we're trying to do is understand why it matters that
it went to, if it didn't just go to באי הארץ, ba'ei
ha'aretz, it went to באי הארץ ba'ei ha'aretz. and they pass it
back to their fathers and it goes down to their kids. Okay,
that's how you conceptualize it. They all went to the גורן, Goren,
they got ten portions, they passed it up, it came back down
but each got five. Yes? Okay, but the question is why does
that matter? Right? Even if it went to them, they would get
two equal sized portions and they'd pass it down. That's what's happening.
Each family is getting an equal sized portion. These nine have to
divide one portion, this one gets one. Why does it matter that
you start at באי הארץ ba'ei ha'aretz, and you go up and
then go back down? You don't understand the question? Okay, so here's
why it matters. It matters because of the relative amount they get
to other families. All right? If you went, let's imagine this was
another family, not this family. Okay? So if this is, right, if
you divided, if you decided it was gonna go to, if you
decided it was gonna go to what do you call it, to
יוצאי מצרים, Yotzei Mitzrayim, he would get one, he would get one,
he would get one, they pass it down and he'd have, and
he'd have one, they'd have one, they'd have one, right? So that
would be relative. Because it's going לבאי הארץ, all right, in this
case, in this case he has one, they have five, they have
five. You see that? Pass it up, comes back down, five five
and one, these have five times as much as he does.
You understand the difference? If you started here, then they, then each
family would have one. Now because you start down here and go
up and come down, these guys each get five times as much
as this guy gets. And the brothers decided to do this
division independently, irrespective of the fact that brother number one had so
many more kids? They didn't decide, that's the הלכה. Halacha. The הלכה
Halacha is למטות אבותם ינחלו. L'matot avotam yinchalu. You who come into
מצרים Mitzrayim, are לאלה תחלק הארץ. But then you have to get
it through your fathers. We sort of give it to you and
divide it according to the, to you and we give an equal
portion to everybody here. Okay, but then you pass it back to
your fathers and it comes back down to you. So if you're
a big family, here's the way to conceptualize it, if you're a
big family when you go into ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you're gonna
get more, even though you might not get, like because of how
this divides, you might not get, you know, equal to your cousins.
But if you're a big family you're gonna get more when you
come in as opposed to this was a small family, this guy
got less. I totally get that, but I'm talking about the two
brothers, one has nine kids, one has one. Right. They didn't have
to pool all the lots and divide it, right? They had, what
do you mean, it wasn't a choice. It's what the פסוק Pasuk
says, למטות אבותם ינחלו. L'matot avotam yinchalu.
Rebbe's משל, Mashal if he's making you think about how this would
could play out by a deal in real life, that the brothers
made this deal when they went to get the ירושה. Yerusha. But
that's just the משל. The point is the פסוק Pasuk says that's
how it works. They sent their kids to get ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael. the kids gave it back to the fathers and then the
fathers gave it back to the kids. But and you don't have
a choice, that's what the פסוק Pasuk says.
That's the way it works, המתים יורשים את החיים. Ha'metim yorshin et
hachayim.
The משל is confusing you. It's not a deal. Okay, it's what
the פסוק Pasuk is saying, yes. I still don't understand, I mean
why has it to go through this whole complication? Why can't it
just say, as we were saying before, למטות אבותם... L'matot avotam... sort
of direct division? I don't know, I don't know, I don't know
what to say about that. Okay, yes. All of them are from
the same tribe? Yeah, no,
the brothers had to be the same tribe. It all goes by
by father's family, right. Okay, alright. So fine. So that's, by the
way, I'm not even getting to the next level of complexity, which
is a whole debate of רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot about this.
Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara you can read the תוספות. Tosafot.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. By the way, I
just want to say I want one thing to think about as
we're doing this is about are you getting from your fathers, are
you getting and passing back to your fathers and getting from them.
There's a nice way to sort of think about this more, you
know, sort of philosophically, right? About how what does a parents bequeath
to the children, you know, what do the children go ahead and
then are able to bequeath back, you know, to their parents? And
it's also about our relationship to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael How much
is our relationship to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael a sense of, right,
a heritage, you know, and an inheritance or whatever, but the generation
that went in, they conquered the land, you know, how much is
anything we experience accomplish in life, what we do ourselves or what
we've gotten from our parents, you know? So I think there's a
lot of power to the different models that are being presented here.
Is there a ירושלמי Yerushalmi coming up on this? Something on this
like the whole ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael מתים יורשים את החיים? Well
there is. First of all we have a third opinion here, okay.
רב שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, Reb Shimon ben Elazar Omer, רב שמעון
אלעזר Reb Shimon Elazar said, לאלו ולאלו
נתחלקה הארץ, l'elu u'le'elu nitchalkah ha'aretz, כדי לקיים שני מקראות הללו. kdei
l'kayem shnei mikraot elo. We don't have to make some פשרה, pshara,
they both get it. You have what you have in this life
because of your own accomplishments and you get what you have in
your life, you know, you have ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael because it's
an inheritance from your fathers, right? So it's sort of like you
have both are true and one doesn't, you know, isn't translated into
the other. הכיצד? Ha keitzad? How does that work? היה מיוצאי מצרים
נוטל חלקו עם יוצאי מצרים. Haya miyotzei Mitzrayim, notel chelko im yotzei
Mitzrayim. היה מבאיי הארץ נוטל חלקו עם באיי הארץ. Haya miba'ei ha'aretz,
notel chelko im ba'ei ha'aretz. מכאן ומכאן נוטל חלקו מכאן ומכאן. Mikan
umikan, notel chelko mikan umikan.
So according to him,
okay, if you basically were, okay, there's a third position. This is
a third position, okay. If you're one of these kids, you get,
we divide up basically what we do is, the way we would
have to do it is, we would look at the entire population
of the men over twenty who are יוצאי מצרים, yotzei Mitzrayim, 600,000
and change, the entire population of those that were באיי הארץ, ba'ei
ha'aretz, also 600,000 and change. We'd probably do it tribe by tribe
but let's ignore that for now. 1.2 million, okay, we create 1.2
million portions, all right, and now we distribute those 1.2 million portions
to those that are coming into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and conceptually
to those who left מצרים Mitzrayim who are then going to pass
it on to their kids. All right, so you have to like
consider the entire populations of both, divide it up according to those
portions. So in this type of a case, we would give the
following people, like you'd give all of these people their portions, okay,
this would be a portion, this guy would get a portion, each
of their kids would get a portion, okay, and this guy would
get a portion. So, you know, possibly divided into nine. And these,
wait, all of these, oh and he would pass it down, right.
So each of these kids would get, you know, their portion, right,
and this guy would get one, and this guy would come down,
this one would come down, he would get two, okay, and this
guy would come down and this would be, you know, one-ninth, all
of these little things. Okay.
What? They each get one and one-ninth. And this guy gets two.
Okay. So it's sort of both of them are true. So let's
just read that. הכיצד? Ha keitzad? היה מיוצאי מצרים נוטל חלקו עם
יוצאי מצרים. Haya miyotzei Mitzrayim, notel chelko im yotzei Mitzrayim.
So then you get that and then you would die in the
מדבר midbar and pass it down to your kids, okay. היה מבאיי
הארץ נוטל חלקו עם באיי הארץ, Haya miba'ei ha'aretz, notel chelko im
ba'ei ha'aretz,
and you'd go in and keep that. מכאן ומכאן, Mikan umikan, both
ways, נוטל חלקו מכאן ומכאן. notel chelko mikan umikan. You get it
both ways. Now the question is, who could be the person who
was יוצאי מצרים yotzei Mitzrayim and באיי הארץ? ba'ei ha'aretz? יהושע וכלב!
Yehoshua v'Calev! Right, יהושע וכלב. Yehoshua v'Calev. So here's an... so did
they get double portions, once for יוצאי מצרים yotzei Mitzrayim and one
for באיי הארץ? ba'ei ha'aretz? So this is a big discussion in
תוספות Tosafot because the problem was they were older than 60 years
old. And how much, you know, does it go by the sort
of by the census, which was 20 to 60? Or how much
is it that the actual נחלה of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael was
enough to be over 20 and it wasn't limited to those under
60? So there's a whole long discussion in תוספות Tosafot whether this
could be יהושע וכלב, Yehoshua v'Calev, were they entitled to get as
באיי הארץ ba'ei ha'aretz since they were over 60 years old. So
who was the sister who like knew where the... שרח בת אשר.
Serach bat Asher. Yeah, but the thing is that's a woman, so
unless she's getting through her father or whatever. Oh, and all the
women. What? Men supposed to die in the... Right, so then what's
בנות צלפחד Bnot Tzelofchad petition worked, I mean that's true in general,
once their petition worked there could have been a lot of other
women who got by virtue of that, that their fathers weren't around
and so on and they had only daughters. One minute. So that's
so if it's not יהושע וכלב, Yehoshua v'Calev, what the רשב"ם Rashbam
and תוספות Tosafot say is that it does not mean the same
person, okay. It means that, you know, like we said, this guy
gets as יוצאי מצרים, yotzei Mitzrayim, this guy gets as באיי הארץ,
ba'ei ha'aretz, and then he would get from his father so he
would wind up getting two portions, his own portion and his father's
portion. Okay, but it's interesting whether we're suggesting that somebody could have
been both. You had a question Michael? Oh yeah, I'm trying to
understand, היה מבאיי הארץ נוטל חלקו Haya miba'ei ha'aretz notel chelko if
you're both, מכאן ומכאן נוטל חלקו מכאן ומכאן. mikan umikan notel chelko
mikan umikan. היה מיוצאי מצרים נוטל חלקו עם יוצאי מצרים, Haya miyotzei
Mitzrayim notel chelko im yotzei Mitzrayim, היה מבאיי הארץ נוטל חלקו עם
באיי הארץ, Haya miba'ei ha'aretz notel chelko im ba'ei ha'aretz, מכאן ומכאן
נוטל חלקו מכאן ומכאן, mikan umikan notel chelko mikan umikan, does that
mean just one portion or two? Two! Both! מכאן ומכאן. Mikan umikan.
Yeah but that's what I'm trying to say, you're just one person,
why are you getting two? Because you were entitled to a portion
as יוצאי מצרים yotzei Mitzrayim and entitled as
באיי הארץ. ba'ei ha'aretz. So I'm not inheriting anything from my dad
because you know I'm so... Right. I understand. The issue of יהושע
וכלב, Yehoshua v'Calev, I agree with you. The issue of יהושע וכלב
Yehoshua v'Calev is not just an interesting and whether they got above
the age of 20. It's like whether you can double dip. Right.
I understand. Like, but I think there's a power like as a
יוצאי מצרים yotzei Mitzrayim your generation was like awarded the land of
Israel, but you failed to receive it. As a באי הארץ, ba'ei
ha'aretz. you know, it's... I understand. It's like, can you get it
double?
The other point I want to make, I want to remind you
is this issue of under the age of 20, right? It's actually
helpful that you have it both ways. Because if this person left
under the age of 20 and his father didn't leave and he
had all these kids, at least the kids are getting by virtue
of themselves. Or the reverse, if this kid was under the age
of 20 and he's not going to get by virtue of himself,
at least he's going to get by virtue of his father. The
worst case scenario is somebody left under the age of 20 and
had a kid under the age of 20. Right. Then it still
wouldn't work. Okay, which is definitely possible. Okay. Even if he didn't
leave Egypt, this underaged child is going to receive as opposed to
the underaged child whose father died, right?
One more time? If the father... what if the father didn't leave
Egypt? Like died in Egypt and the kid left underage? No, but
he didn't die. He didn't... why did he not leave? Are there
any cases where the father stayed? No, I mean there's מדרשים midrashim
about people dying at whatever but... look, yeah. Okay fine. Alright. So
now let's see, now the גמרא Gemara continues. גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Okay. So... let me just check one thing here about this רבנו
תם. Rabbeinu Tam. Hold on.
Okay, I won't get into that. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Now, מרגלים, Meraglim, now who got the second... who got
the portion of the מרגלים? Meraglim? Okay, since now, you know, those
were יוצאי מצרים, yotzei Mitzrayim, so assuming it was going this... presumably
this is going still according to this opinion that it was both
יוצאי מצרים yotzei Mitzrayim and באי הארץ. ba'ei ha'aretz, So now we
have to wonder about the people that should have gotten,
but somehow there was a sense that they lost their right to
it. So there's a sense that the מרגלים... Meraglim... he says that
there was a ספרי, Sifrei, he said, they were רשעים. reshaim. Right,
right.
So and so because the גמרא Gemara is also going to make
a דרשה, drashah, it says... so it says לא בשל מרגלים יהושע
וכלב נטלו חלקם. lo b'shel Meraglim Yehoshua v'Calev natlu chelkam. So יהושע
וכלב Yehoshua v'Calev got it. Now, how do we know that the
מרגלים, Meraglim, you know, okay, they were רשעים, reshaim, but still maybe
they got it and they passed it on to their kids. So
as Rabbi Dov just said, there's a ספרי Sifrei that says כאלה
means that they have to not be רשעים. reshaim. The earlier דרשה
drashah לאלה כאלה, la'eleh ka'eleh, that if they're רשעים, reshaim, you didn't
get it, but that doesn't mean that it was like a lot
of, like anybody who was you know not a normal run-of-the-mill רשע,
rasha, only the big names רשעים reshaim in the stories there.
But the other thing is a specific דרשה drashah from the פסוק.
pasuk. It says by יהושע וכלב, Yehoshua v'Calev, it says חיו מן
האנשים האלה. chayyu min ha'anashim ha'eleh. They survived from these people, from
the מרגלים. Meraglim. So the דרשה drashah is they survived, they were
sort of enriched from the מרגלים, Meraglim, that they inherited what should
have gone to the מרגלים. Meraglim. So the kids of the מרגלים
Meraglim now were out. But if they were באי הארץ, ba'ei ha'aretz
that's again nice when you have this דרשה drashah of יוצאי מצרים
yotzei Mitzrayim and באי הארץ. ba'ei ha'aretz, That even if you didn't
get by virtue of your fathers, because your father was underage or
your father was one of the מרגלים, Meraglim, you're able to get
by your own you know virtue. I really like this approach that
it's to both, because it speaks to a reality of like our
lives, you know, about what we get from our parents and what
we accomplish on our own, and sometimes where people are you know
are able to merit both, right, and sometimes it's what you you
know whatever, sometimes you only have one of them. Yeah. So we're
saying they received their inheritance and then they lost it because they
were רשעים. reshaim. Right. They were assigned a חלק chelek because they
were יוצאי מצרים yotzei Mitzrayim and then the חלק chelek was handed
over to יהושע וכלב, Yehoshua v'Calev, exactly. Okay now.
They weren't רשעים reshaim at the moment they were יוצאי מצרים. yotzei
Mitzrayim. That's a good point too. מתלוננים ועדת קרח, Mitlonenim v'adat Korach,
the complainers. Now who are the complainers? There's a lot of good
candidates for that. ויהי כמתלוננים רע באזני השם, Vay'hi kamitlonenim ra b'oznei
Hashem, right, so you would have thought I would have thought it
was that. The גמרא Gemara later's going to say it means the
מתלוננים mitlonenim of עדת קרח. adat Korach. It means the
250 men who whatever. So they לא היה להם חלק בארץ. lo
hayah lahem chelek ba'aretz. They did not get a portion. והבנים נטלו
בזכות אבי אביהם, V'habanim natlu bizchut avi avihem,
and the sons got by virtue of their grandfathers. So what does
this mean? So it says so because since the פסוק pasuk says
by צלפחד, Tzelafchad, and this is another way that we know that
the רשעים reshaim did not... were not entitled, because it says אבינו
מת במדבר והוא לא היה בעדת השם... avinu meit bamidbar v'hu lo
hayah b'adat Hashem... what is it בנועד... b'no'ad... what's the פסוק? pasuk?
Michael just said.
והוא לא היה בעדת השם... v'hu lo hayah b'adat Hashem... come on,
what's...
what?
I know. They say that he wasn't with קרח. Korach. Okay.
כי בחטאו... Ki v'cheto... אבינו מת במדבר והוא לא היה בתוך העדה
הנועדים על השם בעדת קרח כי בחטאו מת ובנים לא היו לו,
Avinu meit bamidbar v'hu lo haya b'toch ha'eida hano'adim al Hashem ba'adat
Korach ki v'cheto meit u'vanim lo hayu lo, which means, had he
been with עדת קרח, Adas Korach, we would have understood why he
wasn't getting a portion. So implicit in that is that עדת קרח
Adas Korach did not get a portion בארץ. Now, what does it
mean that they got בזכות אבי אביהם? bizchut avi avihem? So if
these were עדת קרח Adas Korach and these were the kids, right?
But if their fathers also left מצרים, Mitzrayim right? If the fathers
of עדת קרח Adas Korach also left מצרים, oh, now both of
my pens aren't working. Wonderful. Okay.
Wonderful. Anyway, I go through these pens faster than... anyway, if the
fathers of עדת קרח, Adas Korach, if these were עדת קרח, Adas
Korach, okay, and the fathers and all of these were יוצאי מצרים,
yotzei Mitzrayim, okay, then the kids wouldn't get by virtue of their
fathers, but their grandfather would still pass down through their fathers and
go to the kids. Yeah, to the grandkids. Their grandfather was also...
yeah, you could have, right, a father and a son that were
both over twenty when they יוצאי מצרים. yotzei Mitzrayim. So if these
all were יוצאי מצרים, yotzei Mitzrayim, their kids didn't get by virtue
of the fathers, but their kids could get by virtue of the
grandfather, okay, בזכות אבי אביהם. bizchut avi avihem. Okay, so fine.
So now the גמרא Gemara continues, let me just check.
Right, אם היו מיוצאי מצרים. im hayu mi-yotzei Mitzrayim. Right. Hold on,
I'm just checking.
Right. Okay, yeah. So the difference between the מתלוננים, mislonanim, between עדת
קרח Adas Korach and the מרגלים meraglim is the מרגלים, meraglim, the
portion that was assigned to them was actually given to יהושע Yehoshua
and כלב, Kalev, whereas the עדת קרח, Adas Korach, the portion that
was assigned to them wasn't given to anybody. It was basically, they
were, you know, it was like they were struck from the list
and it was equally divided like, you know, conceptually amongst everybody. So
that wasn't assigned at all. They weren't even assigned a portion as
opposed to יהושע Yehoshua and כלב, Kalev, they were, the מרגלים meraglim
were assigned and it went to יהושע Yehoshua and כלב. Kalev. Yes.
Those מרגלים meraglim are from all the tribes. Right. So does that
mean יהושע Yehoshua and כלב Kalev have... oh yeah, I guess that's
a good point. That's an interesting question. When you say that the
חלק was assigned, was it, was the חלק assigned in those tribes?
And yeah, that's an interesting conceptual thought, like did יהושע Yehoshua and
כלב Kalev have a little piece of every שבט? shevet? There's something
a little nice conceptually about that idea I think, you know, they
sort of by I don't know... it could just be that it's
then divided. Right, it could just be that it's then divided. Does
that mean that they're tribes' bigger pieces?
Right. Right. Right. Yeah, it's a little... right, it could be, it
could be. The whole question about all this is going to be
is that how much do you start that the section of the
שבט shevet is proportional to the number of people in the שבט,
shevet, you know, or the number of lots in the שבט shevet
as opposed to is it equal. So the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to
get to that. We're going to see that in the גמרא. Gemara.
So let's keep on reading. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
okay, נטלו עלו להם חלקיהן בארץ בנים נטלו בזכות אבי אביהן ובזכות
אבי אמותיהן. natlu, alu lahem chelkehen ba'aretz banim natlu bizchut avi avihen
u'bizchut avi imoteihen. Oh
look, I forgot about that. So you have אמותיהן, imoteihen, okay, so
the אמותיהן imoteihen wouldn't get on their own merit even if they
were יוצאי מצרים yotzei Mitzrayim because they were women, okay, but if
their fathers were, if their fathers here were יוצאי מצרים, yotzei Mitzrayim,
and then once you have the innovation
of בנות צלפחד, bnot Tzelofchad, right, then you can get through your
maternal grandfather as well. Alright. So these wouldn't get themselves because they
were עדת קרח, Adas Korach, she wouldn't get because she's a woman,
but if the grandfathers were יוצאי מצרים, yotzei Mitzrayim, they would get
and pass on to their grandkids. Alright. In that case, the grandchildren
were all women.
If the grandchildren were all women then they... no, if the grandchildren
were all women, then yeah, if his only child was a daughter,
right, then it would continue, if his only child were a daughter
and her only children were daughters, then yes, it would pass on
even if those were all... then they wouldn't get on their own
merit because as women directly going into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they
wouldn't get, but through their grandfather they would get. Okay. Okay, מאי
משמע דהאי ושמות מטות אבותם ביוצאי מצרים ככתיב? mai mashma de-hai u-shmot
matot avotam biyotzei Mitzrayim ke-ketiv?
How do you know the tribes of the, you know, of the
fathers' tribes talking about יוצאי מצרים? yotzei Mitzrayim? דלמא לשבטים קאמר לה,
dilma lishvatim qamar leh, which is probably פשט pshat. in the פסוקים.
psukim Maybe it means based on the, you know, the twelve sons
of יעקב, Yaakov, which is מטות, the real שבטים. shvatim. Now, whether
that means that
you sort of, you know, divide twelve equal portions and go down
or however that would play out, but we should be thinking about
it in terms of tribes, not just in terms of יוצאי מצרים,
yotzei Mitzrayim, which is how we've been reading it. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, דלמא לשבטים קאמר לה דכתיב... dilma lishvatim qamar leh
dich-ketiv...
The answer is, so here's the answer: ונתתי אותה לכם מורשה אני
ה׳, venasati osah lachem morashah ani Hashem,
which is right one of the first things that משה Moshe tells
בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael about God's promise to them. I am going
to take you out of מצרים and give you the land of
Israel as a, like as a, not bequest, what's the right word
for that? As a heritage. As a legacy. As a heritage. Okay.
ירושה היא לכם מאבותיכם. Yerushah hi lachem me-avoseichem.
You are going to get it from your fathers. Okay. That's what,
that's what God says to the יוצאי מצרים. Yotzei Mitzrayim. ליוצאי מצרים
קאמר. Le-yotzei Mitzrayim ka'amar. So He said it to the יוצאי מצרים.
Yotzei Mitzrayim. So this is a very powerful point what it's saying
here. It's saying first of all, it's both saying look, משה Moshe
promised those people who were going out of מצרים you're going to
get it. So therefore we have to say that you know, in
a way we're forced to read יוצאי מצרים Yotzei Mitzrayim into the
פסוקים here because משה Moshe. promised it was going to go to
that generation that was יוצאי מצרים. Yotzei Mitzrayim. So either they got
it directly or they got it through their kids and passed it
back down, or both and both. But every three approaches has it
also going to יוצאי מצרים Yotzei Mitzrayim because that was part of
the promise. But the powerful thing about this is it wasn't just
saying that it was promised to יוצאי מצרים Yotzei Mitzrayim so obviously
they had to get it. It was saying even יוצאי מצרים Yotzei
Mitzrayim got it as a מורשה, morashah, got it as a ירושה
yerushah from the promise like to the אבות, Avot, from the previous
promise. So it's like everybody is getting it as a ירושה yerushah
as well. Not just directly given to יוצאי מצרים. Yotzei Mitzrayim. Even
for them it's a ירושה. yerushah. But anyway, but the point is
that they are getting it directly, that they were promised it so
it has to be, it has to be also going to יוצאי
מצרים. Yotzei Mitzrayim. Yes? I just think what you said is powerful.
It's sort of almost unusual that the דרשה drasha is contextualizing the
statement historically, right? Isn't the word קאמר להו ka'amar lehu meaning משה
רבנו Moshe Rabbeinu said it to them? In other words, it's משה.
Right. So the historical context requires that it was a ירושה yerushah
to יוצאי מצרים. Yotzei Mitzrayim. Right. That's unusual. That's like putting it
back into its context rather than taking it out of its context.
Right. Now the other thing that I don't know, that I'm thinking
about that's powerful about this is ירושה היא לכם מאבותיכם Yerushah hi
lachem me-avoseichem is both what God is saying to יוצאי מצרים, Yotzei
Mitzrayim, you're getting it בזכות אבות bizchus Avos etc. But I think
what it's also saying is every generation it's important that your relationship
to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. is always has the component of a
sense of ירושה, yerushah, right? So therefore it's every approach you have,
even if it's באי הארץ, ba'ei ha'aretz. it's באי הארץ ba'ei ha'aretz
but through יוצאי מצרים. Yotzei Mitzrayim. Everybody is getting it as a
ירושה. yerushah. So those that go in and conquer the land, right,
you can't just think oh like כוחי ועוצם ידי, kochi ve-otzem yadi,
like I'm getting it through my own merit, right? So for every
generation you have to know you're getting it as a ירושה. yerushah.
So
specifically with באי הארץ, ba'ei ha'aretz. we can't just say it's just
באי הארץ. ba'ei ha'aretz, It's באי הארץ Ba'ei Ha'aretz, by virtue of
יוצאי מצרים, Yotzei Mitzrayim, you know, going back to their fathers and
coming back down. That's so interesting what that does to our psyche
kind of. Like when you get something as a ירושה yerushah what
does it do to your relationship? Right, you maybe take it for
granted or do you treasure it more? Or whatever. Right. I mean
I think that the powerful ideas here are the ones that combine
the two, you know, either have it to be, because then it's
true to our relationship to it, you know?
Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara is going to work through the
פסוקים and see which ones are more supportive, which one supports more
either approach. Yes. Like רש״י Rashi on בראשית, Bereishis, why it begins...
Right, exactly. The same thing? Yeah, yeah, exactly. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, okay. סימן לרב פפא ויוסף חפר מנשה
יכניש. Siman le-Rav Papa ve-Yosef Chefer Menashe yachnish. That's the ראשי פרקים
rashei prakim for what are the things we're going to prove. Okay.
אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי. Amar lei Rav Papa le-Abaye. So רב
פפא Rav Papa says to אביי: Abaye: בשלמא למאן דאמר ליוצאי מצרים
נתחלקה הארץ, Bishlama le-man de-amar le-yotzei Mitzrayim nitchalkah ha'aretz, it was given
to יוצאי מצרים, Yotzei Mitzrayim, היינו דכתיב hainu de-ksiv לרוב תרבה נחלתו
ולמעט תמעיט נחלתו, larov tarbeh nachalaso ve-lam'at tam'it nachalaso, that you for
the many you give many and for the small you shrink it.
אלא למאן דאמר לבאי הארץ, Ela le-man de-amar le-va'ei ha'aretz, מאי לרוב
תרבה נחלתו? mai larov tarbeh nachalaso? What does it mean to the
many you should increase it? קשיא. Kashya. Now
what? What's the problem with the פסוק, pasuk, right? If you go
back to this, here we'll erase the עדת קורח Adas Korach and
these guys here. Okay. You go back to this, this is your
יוצאי מצרים Yotzei Mitzrayim and your באי הארץ. Ba'ei Ha'aretz, Okay. So
it works, I would say it works even better, right? If you're
whatever. If you're a, you know, if you're a לרוב תרבה נחלתו
ולמעט תמעיט נחלתו, larov tarbeh nachalaso ve-lam'at tam'it nachalaso,
the simple sense is it's referring to those who are going in.
If you're a lot of people you give them a lot. If
there's few people you give them a little. That would make sense
if we're talking about distributing it based on באי הארץ, Ba'ei Ha'aretz
right? So why does it work better if it's talking about יוצאי
מצרים? Yotzei Mitzrayim? Because
it makes it more like... ah, excellent. So that's what רשב"ם Rashbam
says is the point isn't לרב Larav give a lot. It's לרב
Larav increase and למעט Lama'at you should shrink it. So meaning
that what it's saying is that if you imagine that this was,
so it's again it's funny that the גמרא's Gemara reading this as
פשט, but if it was saying that imagine in this case you
had, right,
whatever.
This
family let's not do it with different brothers, let's do it like
this. I mean whatever, it is different brothers, okay? And they have
however many kids that they've got. And this family's got
a lot of יוצאי מצרים Yotzei Mitzrayim and only a few kids,
okay? So this is a big family of יוצאי מצרים Yotzei Mitzrayim
and a small number going in. And this is a small family
of יוצאי מצרים Yotzei Mitzrayim and a big number going in. So
it says לרב, Larav, there could be something that was a big
family, but תמעיט נחלתו. Tam'it Nachalato. They're going to have to shrink
it if the people going in is a smaller number. And למעט,
Lama'at, and even if it was a small family, I'm sorry, לרב
Larav did I read it wrong?
Yes. And if it's many, thank you, thank you, thank you, sorry,
I'm getting myself confused. Sorry, if it's many, but you're going to
increase what you would have thought, you would have thought this guy
would get one portion, but because there were many that preceded him,
he's going to get they're going to get like a bigger portion.
You should increase it. And so
that's in this case the
למעט, Lama'at, if there was a small number of forebearers, תמעיט נחלתו.
Tam'it Nachalato. Even though there's a lot of kids, they're going to
be dealing with a lot less because of their forebearers. At first,
I thought it was a motivation for יוצאי מצרים Yotzei Mitzrayim to
go through the מדבר Midbar to go in ארץ ישראל. That only
works if there were a lot of יוצאי מצרים Yotzei Mitzrayim and
only then a small number. Right. It doesn't work the other way.
Yeah. So what's why what's motivating the דרשה? Derashah? I don't know.
Anyway, that's what and the גמרא Gemara says קשיא, Kashya, but it
says the other way to just read it to many give a
lot and to few give a few, the גמרא Gemara says like
then it wouldn't say תרבה Tarbeh and תמעיט, Tam'it, which sounds like
you're changing it from what it should be. You're growing it and
you're shrinking it. So it says קשיא. Kashya. And of course, that's
not such a קשיא. Kashya. I mean, it's really complicated. You see,
I even got confused explaining that. But but so it's not exactly
clear why the גמרא Gemara thinks that פסוק Pasuk works so much
better. תוספות Tosafot has a different גרסא. Girsa. תוספות's Tosafot גרסא Girsa
is, let me see, תוספות's Tosafot גרסא Girsa is, let me just
double-check
it, בין רב למעט. Bein Rav Lama'at. So the תוספות's Tosafot גרסא
Girsa is that there's another פסוק. Pasuk. It
says לאלה תחלק הארץ בין רב למעט, La'eleh Techalek Ha'aretz Bein Rav
Lama'at, whether a lot or a little. So what does that mean
whether a lot or a little? So that גמרא Gemara says, well,
if it's talking about יוצאי מצרים, Yotzei Mitzrayim, you understand, it says
don't pay attention to whether this generation is a lot or a
little, right? Because it doesn't go by this generation. It goes by
יוצאי מצרים. Yotzei Mitzrayim. So that works better to say that's referring
to, that's telling you don't look, right, בין רב למעט Bein Rav
Lama'at is actually in direct contradiction to לרב תרבה נחלתו ולמעט תמעיט
נחלתו, Larav Tarbeh Nachalato Velama'at Tam'it Nachalato, right? So how do you
what do those those words mean? So the גמרא Gemara says בין
רב למעט Bein Rav Lama'at says ignore this generation, look at the
previous one. Okay, so that's a better גרסא Girsa in the גמרא.
Gemara. Makes it more clear what's bothering the גמרא. Gemara.
Yeah, I mean or exactly. It's right, quoting it that the גמרא's
Gemara quoting a different פסוק. Pasuk. How did that happen? Like could
the scribe have been like... Well, it sounds like look at the
second line of the רשב"ם. Rashbam. It sounds like the רשב"ם Rashbam
didn't like the גרסא Girsa and he changed it, which often happens
with רש"י Rashi too. But they knew these things by heart, right?
So someone was like, well, that's not really the פסוק Pasuk he
meant. He meant... Could be. Look at the second line in the
רשב"ם. Rashbam. ולא גרסינן מאי בין רב למעט. Velo Garsinan Mai Bein
Rav Lama'at. Okay? Second line on the top of the רשב"ם Rashbam
on קכ"ב. Kuf Chaf Bet. So that's exactly what it says. No,
actually that was the גרסא. Girsa. Okay, so the רשב"ם Rashbam says...
Right. Okay. So let's just read one more פסוק. Pasuk. ואמר ליה
רב פפא לאביי, Va'amar Lei Rav Pappa Le'Abaye, בשלמא למאן דאמר ליוצאי
מצרים, Bishlama Leman De'amar Le'Yotzei Mitzrayim, היינו דקצווחן בנות צלפחד. Hainu Dekatzvachan
Benot Tzelafchad. If it's יוצאי מצרים, Yotzei Mitzrayim, we get why בנות
צלפחד Benot Tzelafchad were complaining because they were saying, look, our father's
entitled, he's not around, we should get our father's portion. Okay, אלא
למאן דאמר לבאי הארץ, Ela Leman De'amar Le'Ba'ei Ha'aretz, אמאי צווחן? Amai
Tvachan? הלא ליתנהו דלשקלו. Halo Leitnehu Delishkalu. But if it's the באי
הארץ, Ba'ei Ha'aretz then they have to be arguing they're entitled to
it on their own and they were never saying, right, they were
not so radical to
say we should be entitled on our own. They were just saying
like we should be able
to replace our father. We should be able it shouldn't pass to
father as you know we should be able to get from our
father. But if you are, but if it's going to
באי הארץ, Ba'ei Ha'aretz then what are they complaining about? It's never
like the land was initially distributed to any man in the family
that they now are asking that we should get by virtue of
that person. They would have to be making a different argument. They
would have to be making that we should be getting on our
own merit, which is not something that they were making. Right? So
what were they complaining? אלא, so the גמרא Gemara says no, there
is an answer. Does everyone understand the question? Right? I mean, obviously
they wouldn't get either way, but the גמרא Gemara is saying in
the context of what they were making their complaint, they wouldn't have
thought to complain if they had to argue to get it on
their own merit. They were only arguing to get it by virtue
of their father, which only makes sense if it's יוצאי מצרים. Yotzei
Mitzrayim. He said באי הארץ Ba'ei Ha'aretz? was the Mesechtem. That's what
the גמרא Gemara is going to say. אלא לחזרה וליטול בנכסי חפר.
Ella lachazara u-litol be-nichsei Chefer. So as Eli correctly understands, no, no,
no. Since in the end of the approach, even באי הארץ Ba'ei
Ha'aretz. get it and give it back to their fathers and then
are יורש yoresh from their fathers, what they are saying is hey
look, if we were sons, then we would have gotten it and
passed
it back to our father or back to חפר Chefer or whatever
or our father, if our father had sons, right, they would have
all passed back and then we would have gotten it that way.
So
we want to get by—it's a little funny like the claim that
they should be allowed to pass back is sort of on their
own merit. But ultimately what they're saying is that if our father
had sons, then our father would have his own portion through the
sons. Because remember the way it works באי הארץ Ba'ei Ha'aretz. is
you divide according to those who come in, you imagine that you
pass it back to all the family and divide it among the
brothers and then you pass it back down. Remember that מת עם
יורשי החיים? Meis im yorshei ha-chayim? So what they're saying is if
our father had sons, then our father would have a portion and
then the sons would have inherited the portion. Right? So are you
telling us just because we're daughters and not sons, that's going to
mean that our father isn't going to get the portion he's entitled
to? So they're still arguing by virtue of our father. Our father.
But it's a little funnier because the father is entitled to the
portion through normally what would have been sons. And here they're saying
but through us, right, he would have been entitled to that portion
and are you telling us that just because if we had been
sons, our father would have had a portion and now because we're
daughters our father doesn't have a portion? And that was precisely בנות
צלפחד's Bnot Tzelofchad argument. No, their argument was, are you telling us
because we're daughters we don't get our father's portion? And what's going
to happen to our father's portion that he always had and we're
not getting and it should pass away from us? Here it's
saying the father doesn't have a portion to begin with because you're
girls. You're saying but had we been boys, he would have had
a portion and then—so are you telling us because we're girls, he
shouldn't get the portion that he would have had had we been
boys as באי הארץ? Ba'ei Ha'aretz. Yeah. So it's a harder argument.
Yeah. Is there also an argument though that if the uncles had
children, they would have gotten something and then it would be split
among צלפחד? Tzelofchad? Oh, that's a good point too. But it seems
like the uncles are באי הארץ. Ba'ei Ha'aretz, Oh, so maybe you're
right. Maybe I misinterpreted this.
So because these guys were
באי הארץ. Ba'ei Ha'aretz, But maybe that's the point. Maybe what they're
saying is forget the portion we would have got. Our uncles are
going to get a portion. They're באי Ba'ei, הארץ. That's why the
גמרא Gemara says חפר. Chefer. I think you're absolutely correct. Our uncles
are באי הארץ, they would have got a portion, they would have
passed it back to חפר, Chefer, and then צלפחד Tzelofchad would have
gotten
by virtue
of and then it would have passed down this way, right, the
portion that would have come through our uncles. I think you're absolutely
correct. That's a better פשט. It makes their argument stronger. Right? It's
not saying that had we been boys, our father would have had
a portion. That's the whole problem. You're not boys. You don't start
with a portion. But he says no, we do start with a
portion because our uncles are באי הארץ, they get a portion, it
goes up, then it gets divided equally, and this portion that would
have come through our uncles is ones that we would have inherited
had we been boys and now you're going to tell us we're
not going to get it. So then they don't get the double
portion? That according to this they would not. That's why our משנה
mishna clearly assumes that
it's יוצאי מצרים. Yotzei Mitzrayim. This is assuming באי, so it would
not have been a double portion. But I think that's absolutely the
best read, you're correct. Yes. So the daughters when they're making their
claim, they're saying that their father didn't die
as same sin as קורח, Korach, because we were saying earlier that
that whole group didn't get any portion. Right? So are they saying
in that sense he deserves a portion as opposed to that group?
Yeah, yeah, that's what we learned before that עדת קורח Adat Korach
did not get. No but I'm saying they're making that distinction about
their father to say that he deserves a portion. Yeah. Yeah. Wait
a minute.
Yeah, so now I'm rereading the רשב"ם Rashbam and it basically says
exactly what you said, שהם אחי אבינו נחלו. she-hem achei avinu nachalu.
שהם אחי אבינו נחלו להחזיר אותו לחבל אביהם. shehem achei avinu nachalu
lehachzir oto lachevel avihem. That's absolutely the right read of the גמרא.
Gemara. So thank you for that. So what they're arguing is no,
no, no. Our father would get a portion not by virtue of
us, but our father minimally would get a portion by virtue of
our uncles who are coming in the land and it would pass
up and get divided, and that's the portion that we should get.
So thank you. That is correct read of the גמרא. Gemara. Okay,
we will end here for today.